なんば　むった
こうほせい
＜私達 宇宙飛行士候補生の➡
The next astronaut candidate training exercise is the Comeback Competition.
次なる訓練は｢カムバック
ちょうせん
コンペティション｣への挑戦｡➡
パラシュートの展開システムや
せいぎょ
自動制御のローバーを作り➡
It's a contest where you compete to reach the goal
どのぐらい正確にゴールに
たどり着けるかを競う大会だ＞
by building everything from the parachute deployment system to the rover.
タイヤをスポンジで作ろう｡
We can make the tires out of sponge!
《何!?考えたこともなかった…》
What?
I never considered that!
で 次はパラシュートだけど…｡
Next comes the parachute.
う～ん…パラシュートの…➡
I'm willing to give you one piece of advice about the parachute.
｢パ｣ぐらいは
教えてやってもいいかな｡
ピコに誘われまして…
酒に付き合えって｡
Well, Pico invited me to have a drink with him.
ピコが…君をですか？
ぼく
ええ｡何故だか僕だけ｡
Pico invited you?
For some reason, I was the only one.
しんぼう
《あと５日｡あと５日の辛抱だ｡➡
Five more days.
I just have to deal with this for five more days...
ヒビト達を乗せたオリオンが
５日後に帰ってきて…➡
In five days, Hibito and the other astronauts will return in Orion.
パラシュートが
しゅんかん
バッと開いた瞬間…》
The moment the parachutes deploy...
おれ
《ようやく俺は解放される…》
I'll finally be free.
チェッ！俺を置いてきやがって｡
このせっかち野郎が｡
You ditched me, you impatient bastard.
(ピコ)ヘッ 俺がこんなヤツ
気に入る訳ねえだろ！
How could I ever like this guy?
ただ こいつは こう見えて
失敗に前向きなんだ｡
It's just, he's pretty positive about failure.
そこが何か こう…なっ｡
And that was...
You know?
本気でやった場合に限るよ｡
本気の失敗には価値がある｡
Only if you're earnest about it.
An earnest failure has meaning.
(リック)⦅本気の失敗には…➡
An earnest failure
価値がある⦆
has meaning...
⦅俺は将来 管制官になり➡
In the future, I'll be a flight director,
宇宙飛行士になったビンスに
指示を送る｡➡
relaying instructions to the astronaut Vince.
そのビンスは
ピコの作った宇宙船に乗る⦆
And Vince will be riding in a spaceship Pico built.
⦅さあ立てよ！⦆
Stand up!
ちか
⦅誓いのサイン 今日の分だ⦆
Time for today's promise sign.
⦅｢誓いのサイン｣は
僕たち３人の目指す先が➡
The promise sign was meant to symbolize that we three were always aiming for space.
いつも宇宙を向いている
ということを意味した⦆
SPACE BROTHERS
You've always been in my heart
But you don't say a thing or even smile
We've always been together
We're ignorant, but we believe
All the time I spent with you
Felt like a dream
We connected the stars and drew pictures
To our hearts' content
Let our hearts, shivering in excitement,
Use the sky as a canvas
And merge to form an everlasting image
#59 Promise Sign
What are you looking for?
何 さがしてんの？さっきから｡
俺の思い出の品だ｡
お前には関係ねぇ｡
A memento of mine.
It's none of your business.
あれ…どこに入れたっけ？
Huh? Where did I put it?
ポケットに
どんだけ もの入れてんだ｡
How much junk do you keep in your pockets?
Ever heard of something called a bag?
カバンっていう便利な道具も
売ってんだよ？
Oh, there it is.
おう あった｡これだ｡
There we go...
You still have that thing?
まだ そんなもの…
持ってたんですか？
あ？お前は持ってねぇ
ってのか？
Huh? You don't have yours?
What is that?
何 それ？ねえ それ何？
Hey, what is it?
Come on... Tell me!
ねっ ねえ！
ろてん
⦅鉱山で露天掘りの就職
説明会がまたある｡日曜だ⦆
The mine will be holding another career fair.
This Sunday.
⦅前回 行かなかったんだろう｡
ビンス｡➡
You didn't attend the last one, Vince.
今回は ちゃんと行けよ⦆
Be sure you attend this one.
(教師)⦅親父さんが わざわざ
連絡してきたぞ｡➡
Your father called me.
うちの子が説明会に来るように
指導してくださいってな⦆
He asked me to help convince his son to attend the career fair.
(ビンス)⦅父さんが!?⦆
Dad called you?
(教師)⦅わかったな 言う通りに
しろよ ビンス｡➡
Understand?
Do as you're told, Vince.
これ以上 大人に
迷惑をかけるな⦆
Don't make it difficult on us adults.
(ピコ)リック｡
Rick...
Pico, about today's meeting...
ピコ！今日のミーティングは…
あれ？
Huh?
ピコ！どうした？その顔｡
Pico, what happened to your face?
ああ…すべって転んだのかい？
こお
地面 凍ってんもんね｡
Oh, did you slip and fall?
The ground's frozen solid...
違うよ！
That wasn't it.
It was my dad.
親父だ｡
悪い リック｡今日はロケットの
ミーティング 行けねぇわ｡
Sorry, Rick.
I can't make the rocket meeting today.
親父の手伝いに行かねぇと｡
I have to go help my dad.
そ そうか…｡
R-Really...
But you'll be free Sunday, right?
ああ！でも日曜は空いてんだろ！
ロケットの材料の買い出し
付き合えよ！➡
Help me buy the materials for our rocket.
じいちゃんが
車 出してくれるんだ！
My grandpa can drive us.
(ピコ)ごめん 日曜は鉱山で
説明会なんだ｡
Sorry,
but on Sunday, the mine's having a career fair.
If I don't go,
行かなきゃ こっち側にも
アザができる｡
I'll have a matching one on this side.
ビンスも今回は行くって
言ってた｡
Vince said that he was going, too.
(リック)そうか…｡
(ピコ)ごめんな リック｡
Oh...
Sorry, Rick.
いや…｡
It's okay.
うわっ イテ！
Ow!
(生徒)アハハ！
(生徒)転びすぎだぞ！リック｡
You fall down too much, Rick.
That had to hurt.
ちゃんと足元を見てないから
転ぶんだ リック｡
You trip because you don't watch the ground, Rick.
てんとう
進路も同じだ｡転倒せずに入れる
現実的な行き先を考えとけよ｡
The same could be said of your future.
You should be realistic when you select a career.
わかったな お前も あの２人の
ように正しい選択をしろ｡
Got it?
You should make the right choice, the way the other two did.
あの２人？
The other two?
ピコとビンスだよ｡２人とも
行き先を工業専門学校に決めたぞ｡
Pico and Vince.
They've decided on technical school.
もう必要ねぇもんな｡
We don't need these anymore...
Yeah...
(ﾘｯｸ)待てよ お前ら！ハァハァ…｡
Hold on, guys!
じょうだん
何の冗談だ！ハァハァ…｡
Is this some kind of joke?
誓いのサイン 今日の分だ｡
Time for today's promise sign.
すまん リック｡
Sorry, Rick.
ごめん…もう…誓えない｡
I'm sorry.
But we can't anymore.
リック…宇宙への夢は
最初から俺たちには でかすぎた｡
Rick,
going to space was too big a dream for us.
自分のことは自分で
わかってるつもりだ｡
I know my limits.
テンションの上がる
仕事じゃねぇが➡
A mining engineer isn't the most exciting job,
鉱山技師も悪くない｡
but it isn't bad, either.
(リック)ふざけんな…｡➡
Don't give me that.
本気で言ってんのか!?
バカヤロウ｡➡
Are you serious?
Fools...
こんな ど田舎の街で宇宙に本気で
あこが
憧れた３人が出会えたんだ｡➡
Three space lovers
managed to find one another out in the sticks.
俺は それだけでも
きせき
奇跡だと思ってた！➡
I considered that a miracle in itself!
クッ！お前らのこと
兄弟みたいに思ってたんだ！
I thought of you as brothers!
If you aren't willing to bump fists, then forget it.
こぶし
拳を合わせる気がねぇんなら
もういいよ｡➡
勝手に鉱山でも どこへでも
行ってくれ｡
You can work in the mines if you want.
あきら
俺は絶対に諦めねぇからな！
I'll never give up!
(ﾋﾞﾝｽの声)僕とピコは この日の事を
死ぬほど後悔した｡➡
For the rest of our lives,
Pico and I would regret that day.
後悔なんて言葉じゃ…
全く足りないほどに｡
Regret doesn't come close to describing our feelings.
Rick...
(ﾋﾞﾝｽの声)リックは…事故で死んだ｡
僕とピコが➡
...died in an accident.
It happened the afternoon Pico and I
説明会に行っていた
日曜の午後に｡
attended the career fair.
It happened due to a scrape with a truck.
(保安官)⦅トラックとの
接触事故ですね｡➡
乗用車の方は 凍結した路面に
ハンドルを取られて…｡➡
The passenger car skidded across the icy road,
そのまま 湖に⦆
ending up in the lake.
ハァ…ハァ…｡
ヒッ…ハァ…｡
(教師)今日も来てないですか
ピコとビンス｡➡
Pico and Vince are absent again?
もう ２週間経つというのに…｡
They haven't been here for two weeks...
まあ 親友のリックがいなく
なったんだ｡無理もないでしょう｡
Well, their friend, Rick, passed away.
You can't blame them.
リックに 何度謝っても
謝りきれなかった…｡
I can never apologize enough to Rick...
Why...
(ピコ)なんで なんで
俺は あの時…｡
Why did I...
I know how you feel, Pico.
(ビンス)分かってるよ ピコ！
僕だって 同じだ｡
I feel the same way.
I've made up my mind.
(ﾋﾞﾝｽ)僕は もう決めたんだ｡
迷ってるヒマなんてない｡➡
There's no time to waste.
人生は…短いんだ！
Life is short!
ああ そうだ｡テンションの
上がらねえことに➡
Yeah, that's right.
We can't waste time on stuff that doesn't excite us!
パワー使ってる場合じゃねえ！
現在
(ﾌﾚﾃﾞｨ)遥かに遠い 旅先は
生まれる前より➡
We head for a distant destination, one that predates us.
そこにある｡嗚呼 何故に
人は 宇宙に魅せられ➡
Ah, why are humans inspired to depart, entranced by space?
旅をするのか｡
その答えは 何光年先で➡
How many light-years will it take to discover that answer?
見つかるというのだろう｡
そう 我々は宇宙の旅人｡➡
Yes, we are travelers in space.
重力を出しては また
新たな重力に導かれ➡
Travelers that depart by escaping gravity, and arrive by stepping back in gravity.
降り立つ旅人…｡ロシア
アメリカ 日本…｡国は違えど➡
Russia, America, Japan...
We may come from different countries, but we share the same hopes.
ひびと
想いは同じ…｡
(南波 日々人)
《ポエムなげえよ フレディ…》
Your poem's too long, Freddy.
こころざし
さあ 今！志という名の引力に
引き寄せられし ２組の同士が➡
Now is the time!
Gravity will draw two groups of astronauts together for a rendezvous on the moon!
世紀の月面ランデブーを
果たすのです！
Ring the bell!
ベル ベル！
(ﾌﾚﾃﾞｨ)シップベルと共に 歴史の
ハッチは 開かれる！
The hatch to history will open with a ring of the ship's bell!
(ﾊﾞﾃﾞｨ)ヤッホーゥ！
月面へ ようこそ！
Yahoo!
Welcome to the moon!
アズマー‼
ブカチョフー‼よくぞ無事で！
Azuma!
Pugachev!
Glad you could make it!
あずま
⦅吾妻さん キャッチボール
しませんか？⦆
Azuma, let's play catch.
(吾妻)⦅もう 俺に構うな⦆
You should stay away from me.
Hibito,
⦅ヒビト ＢＲＩＡＮ３号をお前の
もとに送ったのは アズマだ｡➡
Azuma was the one who sent Brian #03 to you.
Azuma trusted Mutta's judgment.
ムッタの提案をアズマが信じた｡➡
かえ
だからお前は 還ってこれたんだ⦆
That's why you made it back alive.
Hibito looks so happy.
日々人のヤツ…
うれしそうな顔しやがる｡
(ｹﾝｼﾞ)いよいよ ４日後
帰還かぁ｡
He'll be returning in four days.
俺達も やっと
南波日々人に会えるわけだ｡➡
We'll finally get to meet Nanba Hibito.
あ そ～いや南波 さっきまで
ビンスさん達と飲んでたんだろ？
Oh, Nanba.
Weren't you out drinking with Vince and Pico?
なに話してたんだよ？
What did you talk about?
Oh,
ああ｡軽く説教されちゃったよ｡
俺が熱出したこととかね｡
they gave me a lecture.
About when I came down with a fever.
How I don't take good enough care of myself and should exercise more.
きた
｢自己管理が甘い 鍛え方が
足りない｣ってね｡
あと 俺がリーダーの時に
新田の携帯を探しに戻った事も…｡
And they also mentioned how I went back to look for Nitta's phone when I was leader.
あの判断は｢決して
正しくはありません｣って｡
My decision...
"Was definitely not correct."
あの砂漠を 月面だと考えれば
むぼう
あんな無謀な行動は➡
If we'd been on the moon, not a desert, we couldn't have done that.
とらなかったはず…ってことだ｡
そうか…あん時は
無理言って悪かったな｡
Yeah... Sorry for dragging you into that.
いや でも こうも言ってたよ｡
Well, he also had this to say.
(ﾋﾞﾝｽ)⦅君達Ｅ班は 一番
アクシデントが多かった｡➡
Team E had the most accidents.
その分 一番成長したと
思って下さい⦆
Which means you've improved the most.
ふぁ～ぁ｡今日は もう
寝よか みんな｡
I'm going to bed...
明日のコンペで
ここでの訓練も終わりだ｡
We're done training for tomorrow's competition.
Wow, look at all the participants.
(北村)うわ～っ！参加者って
こんなにいるんだ｡
I see people who look Japanese.
日本人らしき人も いるよ｡
You're right.
(北村)ほんとだ｡けど 韓国人かも
しれないよ｡中国人かも｡
But they might be Korean...
Or Chinese.
But that one's wearing a Sea Diver T-shirt.
うみんちゅ
いや でもほら｢海人｣の
Ｔシャツ着てるから｡
ふっ こんな乾燥した砂漠で
海人とは…｡
A sea diver in the middle of a desert.
おい！ムッタとケンジ
ちょっと来い！
Hey, Mutta and Kenji...
Come over here.
なんだよ ピコ｡
(ピコ)いや めんどくせえ
ことになった｡
What is it, Pico?
There's a problem.
実は昨夜 雨が降った｡
知ってたか？
It rained last night.
Did you know that?
降ってたっけ…｡
Huh?
Did it rain?
ホテルの周りも ここら辺も
濡れてねえから気付かなかったろ｡
You probably didn't notice because the ground wasn't wet near the hotel or in this area.
きょくち
局地雨だ｡昨日の晩
降りやがった｡そのせいで➡
The rain was limited to a small area.
It happened last night.
As a result, a section of the rover course will be wet.
ローバーが走るコースの辺りが
一部 濡れてる｡
You probably see where I'm going with this.
君らなら もう想像ついてるだろう
もちろん どのチームにとっても➡
The rain will affect every team negatively...
悪条件なのは 同じだが…｡もし
君らのローバーが 濡れた地帯を➡
But if your rover has to pass over wet ground,
通る羽目になったら…スポンジの
タイヤが どうなるか｡
what happens to the sponge tires?
ｽﾎﾟﾝｼﾞのﾀｲﾔは この砂漠競技じゃ
最強だと 俺も思ってたんだけどな｡
I also thought sponge tires would be perfect for a desert competition,
but there had to be a freak shower.
よりによって めったに降らねえ
雨が 降っちまうとは…｡
Wh-What do we do, Kenji?
ど…どうしよっか ケンジ｡
え？う…うん｡
ピコさん ロケットの発射まで
何時間くらいですか？
Pico, how many hours do we have until the rocket launch?
ああ 抽選会が４０分後にある｡
一番を引いちまったら…｡
Ah, the drawing is in forty minutes.
If you're picked to go first,
１時間後には もう空の上だ｡
your rocket will be in the air in an hour.
As you place your hopes on the distant moon
And leave on your journey
You smile in spite of your loneliness
Because you believe in yourself
It doesn't matter if your wings don't match
Spread them out
As you
begin your long journey (try now) (try now)
I'm sure you can make it
Please don't hesitate
to move straight forward
You took
all your pain and sorrow (no more) (no more)
And turned it into your strength
So I'm sure even your destiny to fight many a battle
Is on your side
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#60 Sea Diver and Space Diver
We have to figure out how to keep the tires dry with whatever we can find.
＜手に入るもので ﾛｰﾊﾞｰのタイヤを
濡らさない方法を考えよう＞
Yeah, but we only have twenty-five minutes!
＜ああ｡つっても あと２５分！＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Sea Diver and Space Diver"
I'm not sure, but I can see this working.
＜わからないけど
想像では うまくいってる＞
かお
またそんな顔して
くちびる
唇
噛み締めて